I'm going to talk about your mindset.
سأتكلم عن طريقة تفكيركم
Does your mindset correspond to my dataset?
هل تتوافق طريقة تفكيركم مع قاعدة معطياتي؟
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
If not, one or the other needs upgrading, isn't it?
اذا كان الجواب لا, فان واحدة أو أخرى بحاجة إلى تطوير, أليس كذلك؟
When I talk to my students about global issues,
عندما أتحدث مع طلابي حول القضايا العالمية,
and I listen to them in the coffee break,
وأستمع اليهم خلال استراحات القهوة,
they always talk about "we" and "them."
فغالبا ما اسمعهم يتحدثون عن "نحن" و "هم"
And when they come back into the lecture room
لآحقا, عندما يعودون الى قاعة المحاضرات
I ask them, "What do you mean with "we" and "them"?
اسالهم: "ماذا تقصدون ب"نحن" و"هم"؟
"Oh, it's very easy. It's the western world and it's the developing world," they say.
فيجيبون: "اه الاجابة واضحة: الغرب والعالم النامي"
"We learned it in college."
"لقد تعلمنا ذلك في المدرسة"
And what is the definition then? "The definition?
فما هو تعريفكم؟ "التعريف؟
Everyone knows," they say.
الكل يعرف"
But then you know, I press them like this.
عندها, وكما تعرفون, فانني احب ان استفزهم
So one girl said, very cleverly, "It's very easy.
عندها اجابت فتاة بمنتهى الذكاء:" الفرق واضح,
Western world is a long life in a small family.
العالم الغربي هو حياة اطول وعائلة اصغر.
Developing world is a short life in a large family."
اما العالم النامي فحياة اقصر وعائلة اكبر"
And I like that definition, because it enabled me
لقد اعجبني هذا التعريف لانه اتاح لي
to transfer their mindset
نقل طريقة تفكيرهم
into the dataset.
الى قاعدة معطياتي
And here you have the dataset.
وهنا تجدون قاعدة المعطيات هذه
So, you can see that what we have on this axis here
على هذا المحور تجدون
is size of family. One, two, three, four, five
حجم العائلة: واحدو اثنان, ثلاثة, أربعة, خمسة
children per woman on this axis.
اطفال لكل امرأة, على هذا المحور
And here, length of life, life expectancy,
أما هنا فتجدون متوسط العمر المأمول
30, 40, 50.
30, 40, 50.
Exactly what the students said was their concept about the world.
ما يعبر تماما عن رؤية الطلاب للعالم
And really this is about the bedroom.
هذه النتائج هي عبارة عن قرار يتخذ, في غرفة النوم, بين
Whether the man and woman decide to have small family,
المرأة والرجل. فمع عائلة صغيرة بامكانهم
and take care of their kids, and how long they will live.
الاهتمام اكثر باطفالهم مما يعد بحياة اطول
It's about the bathroom and the kitchen. If you have soap, water and food, you know,
فالقضية تتعلق بالحمام والمطبخ. فكما تعلمون, فان استعمال الصابون وتوفر الماء والطعام
you can live long.
يساهم في اطالة العمر.
And the students were right. It wasn't that the world consisted --
الطلاب كانوا على حق. العالم كان عبارة عن --
the world consisted here, of one set of countries over here,
العالم كان عبارة عن, مجموعة من البلدان - هنا -,
which had large families and short life. Developing world.
مع عائلات كبيرة وحياة قصيرة: العالم النامي.
And we had one set of countries up there
- وفي الاعلى - نجد مجموعة اخرى من البلدان:
which was the western world.
الغالم الغربي
They had small families and long life.
مع عائلات اصغر واعمار اطول
And you are going to see here
الان سوف ترون
the amazing thing that has happened in the world during my lifetime.
التغير المذهل الذي حصل في العالم خلال حياتي.
Then the developing countries applied
البلدان النامية عممت استعمال
soap and water, vaccination.
الماء والصابون والتطعيم
And all the developing world started to apply family planning.
وبدأت بتطبيق سياسات تنظيم الأسرة.
And partly to USA who help to provide
وقد ساعدت الولايات المتحدة, جزئيا, في تأمين
technical advice and investment.
المساعدة التقنية والتمويل
And you see all the world moves over to a two child family,
وكما ترون فالعالم اتجه نحو عائلة من طفلين
and a life with 60 to 70 years.
ومتوسط عمر يتراوح بين 60 و 70 عاما
But some countries remain back in this area here.
مع استثناء بعض الدول التي بقيت في هذا النطاق هنا
And you can see we still have Afghanistan down here.
وتجدون ان افغانستان ما تزال في اسفل الترتيب
We have Liberia. We have Congo.
حيث نجد ايضا ليبيريا والكونغو
So we have countries living there.
اذا بعض الدول ما تزال تعيش في هذا النطاق
So the problem I had
خلاصة هذه التجربة
is that the worldview that my students had
هي أن رؤية طلابي للعالم
corresponds to reality in the world
تتطابق مع الواقع الحقيقي للعالم
the year their teachers were born.
في السنة التي ولد فيها اساتذتهم
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
And we, in fact, when we have played this over the world.
عندما اجريت هذه التجربة اخر مرة
I was at the Global Health Conference here in Washington last week,
كنت هنا في واشنطن, الاسبوع الماضي, في مؤتمر الصحة العالمي
and I could see the wrong concept
وقد رأيت بعض المفاهيم الخاطئة
even active people in United States had,
حتى لدى المثقفين في الولايات المتحدة
that they didn't realize the improvement
لم يستيطعوا ادراك تطور
of Mexico there, and China, in relation to United States.
المكسيك هناك والصين بالمقارنة مع الولايات المتحدة
Look here when I move them forward.
شاهدو هنا عندما اقارنهم
Here we go.
ها نحن ننطلق
They catch up. There's Mexico.
لقد استطاعوا اللحاق. - هنا - المكسيك
It's on par with United States in these two social dimensions.
انها على قدم المساواة مع الولايات المتحدة, في هذين المعيارين الاجتماعيين (حجم العائلة ومتوسط العمر)
There was less than five percent
كان هناك فقط خمسة بالمئة
of the specialists in Global Health that was aware of this.
من الاختصاصيين المشاركين في مؤتمر الصحة العالمي, كانوا على اطلاع على ذلك
This great nation, Mexico,
هذه الامة الكبيرة, المكسيك
has the problem that arms are coming from North,
عندها مشكلة الاسلحة التي تعبر من الشمال
across the borders, so they had to stop that,
عبر الحدود. لذلك عليهم وضع حد لذلك
because they have this strange relationship to the United States, you know.
فكما تعلمون لديهم علاقة "مميزة" مع الولايات المتحدة .
But if I would change this axis here,
الان اذا عدلت هذا المحور, انظروا,
I would instead put income per person.
ووضعت هنا, الدخل الفردي
Income per person. I can put that here.
الدخل الفردي. استطيع وضعه هنا
And we will then see
وسوف ترون
a completely different picture.
صورة مختلفة كليا
By the way, I'm teaching you
بالمناسبة, اني اشرح لكم
how to use our website, Gapminder World,
كيف تستخدمون موقعنا على شبكة الانترنت: Gapminder World.
while I'm correcting this,
لماذا اعرض عليكم ذلك؟
because this is a free utility on the net.
لان استعمال الموقع مجاني على الانترنت
And when I now finally got it right,
واخيرا بعد تعديل كل المعايير
I can go back 200 years in history.
استطيع العودة 200 عاما في التاريخ
And I can find United States up there.
فنجد الولايات المتحدة - هناك -
And I can let the other countries be shown.
واذا اظهرنا باقي البلدان
And now I have income per person on this axis.
والدخل الفردي على هذا المحور
And United States only had some, one, two thousand dollars at that time.
نجد انه كان لا يتعدى 2000 دولار في الولايات المتحدة في ذلك الزمان
And the life expectancy was 35 to 40 years,
اما معدل الاعمار فكان يتراوح بين 35 و 40 عاما
on par with Afghanistan today.
كافغانستان في ايامنا هذه
And what has happened in the world, I will show now.
سوف اعرض عليكم ما حصل في العالم خلال هذه الفترة
This is instead of studying history
فبدل دراسة التاريخ
for one year at university.
لسنة كاملة في الجامعة
You can watch me for one minute now and you'll see the whole thing.
تسطيعون متابعتي لدقيقة واحدة وسوف ترون كل ذلك
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
You can see how the brown bubbles, which is west Europe,
تستطيعون رؤية الفقاعات البنية, التي تمثل أوروبا الغربية
and the yellow one, which is the United States,
والفقاعات الصفراء, التي تمثل الولايات المتحدة
they get richer and richer and also
يزدادون ثراء بالاضافة
start to get healthier and healthier.
الى تحسن الخدمات الصحية
And this is now 100 years ago,
هذا منذ 100 عام
where the rest of the world remains behind.
بينما باقي العالم بقي متأخرا
Here we come. And that was the influenza.
هنا نشاهد تأثير الانفلونزا
That's why we are so scared about flu, isn't it?
لذلك نحن الان خائفون من الانفلونزا, اليس كذلك؟
It's still remembered. The fall of life expectancy.
ما نزال نتذكر الانفلونزا: تدني متوسط العمر المأمول
And then we come up. Not until
ثم بعد ذلك وحتى
independence started.
بدأ عصر الاستقلال
Look here You have China over there,
انظروا الى الصين هناك
you have India over there,
وهنا تجدون الهند
and this is what has happened.
هذا ما حدث في هذه الفترة
Did you note there, that we have Mexico up there?
لاحظوا معي, لدينا المكسيك في الاعلى هناك
Mexico is not at all on par with the United States,
المكسيك ليست على قدم المساواة مع الولايات المتحدة
but they are quite close.
ولكنها ليست بعيدة
And especially, it's interesting to see
ما يثير الاهتمام خاصة هو مقارنة
China and the United States
الصين والولايات المتحدة
during 200 years,
خلال مئتي عام
because I have my oldest son now working for Google,
بما ان ابني الأكبر يعمل الان لدى غوغل
after Google acquired this software.
لقد اشترت غوغل هذه البرمجية
Because in fact, this is child labor. My son and his wife sat in a closet
ان ابني عامل مجتهد: لقد حبس نفسه مع زوجته في خزانة
for many years and developed this.
لعدة سنوات حتى يتمكن من تطوير هذه البرمجية
And my youngest son, who studied Chinese in Beijing.
اما بالنسبة لابني الاصغر فقد درس اللغة الصينية في بكين
So they come in with the two perspectives I have, you know?
فقد اتيا بوجهتي نظر اللتين اتبناهما. أتعلمون؟
And my son, youngest son who studied in Beijing,
فابني الصغير الذي درس في بكين
in China, he got a long-term perspective.
في الصين, قد اكتسب منظورا طويل الاجل
Whereas when my oldest son, who works for Google,
بينما ابني الاكبر, الذي يعمل لدى غوغل
he should develop by quarter, or by half-year.
عليه العمل على اساس فصلي او نصف عام
Or Google is quite generous, so he can have one or two years to go.
وغوغل تعد شركة سخية بامكانه العمل مع رؤية لعام او لعامين قادمين
But in China they look generation after generation
ولكن في الصين يحسبون لمستقبل الأجيال القادمة
because they remember
لانهم يتذكرون
the very embarrassing period, for 100 years,
الفترة المخجلة في تاريخهم, وحيث ولمئة عام
when they went backwards.
كانوا يتراجعون
And then they would remember the first part
ويتذكرون كذلك القسم الاول
of last century, which was really bad,
من القرن الماضي, الذي كان سيئا للغاية
and we could go by this so-called Great Leap Forward.
بعدها نستطيع رؤية المرحلة التي سميت "القفزة الكبيرة الى الأمام"
But this was 1963.
وفي عام 1963
Mao Tse-Tung eventually brought health to China,
ماو تسي تونغ أحضر الصحة الى الصين
and then he died, and then Deng Xiaoping started
ثم توفي. بعدها دنغ كسيابينغ بدأ
this amazing move forward.
رحلة التقدم المذهلة
Isn't it strange to see that the United States
اليس من الغريب رؤية الولايات المتحدة
first grew the economy, and then gradually got rich?
تنمو اقتصاديا في البداية, ثم تصبح غنية بالتدريج
Whereas China could get healthy much earlier,
بينما الصين حققت انجازات في العناية الطبية في وقت اقل
because they applied the knowledge of education, nutrition,
لانهم طبقوا المعرفة في التعليم والتغذية
and then also benefits of penicillin
واستفادوا من البنسلين
and vaccines and family planning.
واللقاحات, وتنظيم الاسرة
And Asia could have social development
وآسيا استطاعت ان تحقق التنمية الاجتماعية
before they got the economic development.
قبل التنمية الاقتصادية
So to me, as a public health professor,
بالنسبة لي, كأستاذ صحة عامة,
it's not strange that all these countries grow so fast now.
لم أتفاجأ ان كل هذه البلدان استطاعت ان تنمو بهذه السرعة
Because what you see here, what you see here
لأن ما ترونه هنا, ما ترونه هنا
is the flat world of Thomas Friedman,
هو "العالم المسطح" كما توقعه توماس فريدمان
isn't it.
اليس كذلك؟
It's not really, really flat.
ليس مسطحا كليا
But the middle income countries --
اما البلدان ذات الدخل المتوسط
and this is where I suggest to my students,
فاني اقترح دائما على طلابي
stop using the concept "developing world."
ان يتوقفوا عن وصفهم ب"العالم النامي"
Because after all, talking about the developing world
لانه وبالنتيجة, الحديث عن العالم النامي
is like having two chapters in the history of the United States.
هو كالحديث عن فصلين من تاريخ الولايات المتحدة
The last chapter is about present, and president Obama,
الفصل الاخير هو عن الحاضر, والرئيس أوباما
and the other is about the past,
والفصل الاخر هو عن الماضي
where you cover everything from Washington
حيث يتحدث عن كل الفترة الممتدة من رئاسة واشنطن
to Eisenhower.
حتى رئاسة ايزنهاور
Because Washington to Eisenhower,
لانه من واشنطن حتى ايزنهاور
that is what we find in the developing world.
كانت الولايات المتحدة كالعالم النامي الان
We could actually go to Mayflower
نستطيع ايضا الانطلاق من مايفلاور
to Eisenhower,
حتى ايزنهاور
and that would be put together into a developing world,
ونعتبر ذلك للعالم النامي
which is rightly growing its cities in a very amazing way,
الذي يطور مدنه بشكل مذهل
which have great entrepreneurs,
ولديه رجال اعمال مهمين
but also have the collapsing countries.
ولكن ايضا فيه بعض البلدان الفاشلة
So, how could we make better sense about this?
كيف نستطيع اعطاء معنى لكل هذه المعطيات؟
Well, one way of trying is to see whether we could
احد السبل المحتملة هو ان نحاول ان نستخرج
look at income distribution.
تورزيع الدخل.
This is the income distribution of peoples in the world,
هذا هو توزيع دخل الشعوب في العالم,
from $1. This is where you have food to eat.
بدءا من دولار واحد: حيث بامكانك تأمين الطعام
These people go to bed hungry.
هؤلاء الناس ينامون وهم جائعون
And this is the number of people.
وهذا هو عددهم
This is $10, whether you have a public or a private
هنا تجدون الناس مع دخل 10 دولارات, حيث باستطاعتهم توفير تأمين صحي
health service system. This is where you can
عام أو خاص. هنا حيث بامكانك
provide health service for your family and school for your children,
توفير تأمين صحي لعائلتك, ومدرسة لاطفالك
and this is OECD countries:
وهنا دول منظمة التعاون والتنمية الاقتصادية
Green, Latin America, East Europe.
وبالاخضر دول اميركا اللاتينية, ثم شرق أوروبا
This is East Asia, and the light blue there is South Asia.
هنا تجدون دول شرق آسيا. وبالأزرق الفاتح دول جنوب آسيا
And this is how the world changed.
الآن سوف تشاهدون كيف تغير العالم
It changed like this.
لقد تغير هكذا
Can you see how it's growing? And how hundreds of millions
هل ترون كيف نما؟ وكيف أن مئات الملايين
and billions is coming out of poverty in Asia?
ومليارات من البشر يتخلصون من الفقر في آسيا
And it goes over here?
حتى نصل الى وقتنا الحاضر
And I come now, into projections,
الان سوف اعرض عليكم التوقعات للمستقبل
but I have to stop at the door of Lehman Brothers there, you know, because --
ولكن علي التوقف عند عتبة بنك ليمان براذرز كما تعلمون. لأن....
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
that's where the projections are not valid any longer.
لأن هذه التوقعات لم تعد صالحة
Probably the world will do this.
على الارجح فان العالم سيتغير هكذا
and then it will continue forward like this.
ثم سيتابع التقدم على هذا الشكل
But more or less, this is what will happen,
على الارجح فان هذا ما سيحدث
and we have a world which cannot be looked upon as divided.
سنحصل على عالم لانستطيع ان نعتبره مقسما.
We have the high income countries here,
لدينا الدول ذات الدخل العالي هنا
with the United States as a leading power;
مع الولايات المتحدة في الطليعة
we have the emerging economies in the middle,
والدول الناشئة في الوسط
which provide a lot of the funding for the bailout;
ما يؤمن كثيرا من التمويل لعمليات الانقاذ الاقتصادي
and we have the low income countries here.
ثم لدينا الدول ذات الدخل المنخفض هنا
Yeah, this is a fact that from where the money comes,
نعم هذه هي الحقيقة فالأموال تأتي من هذه الدول
they have been saving, you know, over the last decade.
فقد كانوا يدخرون الاموال خلال العقد الماضي
And here we have the low income countries
ثم لدينا الدول ذات الدخل المنخفض هنا
where entrepreneurs are.
حيث رجال الاعمال
And here we have the countries in collapse and war,
وهنا نجد الدول التي في حالة انهيار او حرب
like Afghanistan, Somalia, parts of Congo, Darfur.
كأفغانستان, الصومال, اجزاء من الكونغو, دارفور
We have all this at the same time.
نجد كل هذا في ذات الوقت
That's why it's so problematic to describe what has happened
هذه هي الاشكالية التي نجدها حين نحاول وصف ما حدث
in the developing world.
في "العالم النامي"
Because it's so different, what has happened there.
لأن ما حدث كان مختلفا من بلد لآخر
And that's why I suggest
ولهذا اقترح
a slightly different approach of what you would call it.
طريقة أخرى مختلفة لتسميته
And you have huge differences within countries also.
وحتى هنالك اختلافات كبيرة داخل البلدان
I heard that your departments here were by regions.
لقد سمعت ان الولايات هنا (في الولايات المتحدة) تقسم الى مناطق
Here you have Sub-Saharan Africa, South Asia,
هنا نرى افريقيا جنوب الصحراء, جنوب آسيا
East Asia, Arab states,
شرق آسيا, الدول العربية
East Europe, Latin America, and OECD.
شرق أوروبا, أميركا اللاتينية ودول منظمة التعاون والتنمية الاقتصادية
And on this axis, GDP.
وعلى هذا المحور الناتج المحلي الإجمالي
And on this, heath, child survival,
اما على هذا المحور فنرى, الصحة, معدل نجاة الاطفال
and it doesn't come as a surprise
ولا أعتقد ان النتيجة كانت مفاجئة
that Africa south of Sahara is at the bottom.
فافريقيا, جنوبي الصحراء, تأتي في أسفل الترتيب
But when I split it, when I split it
ولكن عندما اقسم النتيجة.... عندما اقسم النتيجة
into country bubbles,
الى فقاعة لكل بلد,
the size of the bubbles here is the population.
حجم الفقاعات يمثل عدد السكان.
Then you see Sierra Leone and Mauritius, completely different.
فان سيراليون وموريشيوس متأخرتان كثيرا
There is such a difference within Sub-Saharan Africa.
هناك اختلافات كبيرة حتى بين دول أفريقيا جنوب الصحراء
And I can split the others. Here is the South Asian,
وباستطاعتي تقسيم بقية الفقاعات. هنا جنوب آسيا,
Arab world.
العالم العربي
Now all your different departments.
والان الولايات المتحدة.
East Europe, Latin America, and OECD countries.
شرق أوروبا, أميركا اللاتينية, ودول منظمة التعاون والتنمية الاقتصادية
And here were are. We have a continuum in the world.
وها نحن الآن, لدينا عالم متصل
We cannot put it into two parts.
لا نستطيع ان نقسمه الى قسمين
It is Mayflower down here. It is Washington here,
ترون مايفلاور في الأسفل هنا. وواشنطن هنا
building, building countries.
بلدان تنمو وتتعمر
It's Lincoln here, advancing them.
ولنكولن يدفع عجلة التقدم
It's Eisenhower bringing modernity into the countries.
ثم أيزنهاور الذي احضر الحداثة للبلد
And then it's United States today, up here.
وها هي الولايات المتحدة اليوم نجدها في الاعلى
And we have countries all this way.
ونجد العديد من الدول على طول الطريق.
Now, this is the important thing
الأن نأتي الى القسم الأهم
of understanding how the world has changed.
وهو كيف نفهم كيف تغير العالم.
At this point I decided to make a pause.
الان اسمحوا لي ان أقوم باعلان ...... ("شكرا لدافعي الضرائب الأميركيين")
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And it is my task, on behalf of the rest of the world,
ومن واحبي, وباسم بقية العالم,
to convey a thanks to the U.S. taxpayers,
أن أشكر دافعي الضرائب الأميركيين
for Demographic Health Survey.
على "الدراسة الديمغرافية للصحة".
Many are not aware of -- no, this is not a joke.
كثير من الناس لايعلمون -- وهذه ليست مزحة.
This is very serious.
وهذا أمر جدي
It is due to USA's continuous sponsoring
فانه بفضل دعم الولايات المتحدة المتواصل
during 25 years of the very good methodology
خلال 25 عاما وبفضل المنهجية المميزة
for measuring child mortality
لاحصاء وفيات الاطفال
that we have a grasp of what's happening in the world.
قد استطعنا معرفة ما يجري في العالم
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
And it is U.S. government at its best,
وحكومة الولايات المتحدة في أفضل عطائها
without advocacy, providing facts,
من دون دفاع, فقط عبر اظهار الأفعال,
that it's useful for the society.
بما يفيد الجتمع
And providing data free of charge
وبتوفير المعلومات مجانا
on the internet, for the world to use. Thank you very much.
على الانترنت, لتكون بمتناول الجميع. شكرا جزيلا.
Quite the opposite of the World Bank,
على العكس تماما من البنك الدولي
who compiled data with government money,
الذي يجمع المعلومات باستعمال مال الحكومات,
tax money, and then they sell it to add a little profit,
أموال الضرائب, ثم يبيعها ليحصل على قليل من الأرباح
in a very inefficient, Gutenberg way.
بطريقة غير فعالة وعلى منهج غتنبرغ
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
But the people doing that at the World Bank
ولكن الأشخاص الذين يؤدن هذه المهمة في البنك الدولي
are among the best in the world.
هم من الأكثر كفاءة في العالم
And they are highly skilled professionals.
ويتميزون بمهارات مهنية كبيرة.
It's just that we would like to upgrade our international agencies
يجب ان نطور المنظمات الدولية
to deal with the world in the modern way, as we do.
لتتعامل مع العالم بطريقة حديثة, كما نفعل نحن
And when it comes to free data and transparency,
وعندما يتعلق الأمر بالمعلومات المجانية والشفافية
United States of America is one of the best.
فان الولايات المتحدة تعد من أفضل الدول
And that doesn't come easy from the mouth of a Swedish public health professor.
وهذا الكلام لا يخرج بسهولة من أستاذ صحة عامة سويدي
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And I'm not paid to come here, no.
ولم يدفع لي احد لأتي الى هنا, لا
I would like to show you what happens with the data,
أود ان اعرض لكم ماذا يحدث للمعلومات التي نجمعها
what we can show with this data.
وماذا يمكننا ان نستخرج منها
Look here. This is the world.
انظروا هنا, هذا هو العالم
With income down there and child mortality.
مع الدخل المنخفض في الأسفل هنا, ووفيات الأطفال
And what has happened in the world?
وماذا حدث في العالم؟
Since 1950, during the last 50 years
منذ عام 1950, وخلال الخمسون عاما الاخيرة
we have had a fall in child mortality.
نلاحظ تراجع معدلات وفيات الأطفال
And it is the DHS that makes it possible to know this.
وبفضل "الدراسة الديمغرافية للصحة" نستطيع معرفة ذلك
And we had an increase in income.
ونجد أيضا زيادة في الدخل
And the blue former developing countries
والبلدان النامية سابقا, باللون الأزرق,
are mixing up with the former industrialized western world.
تندمج مع العالم الغربي الصناعي
We have a continuum. But we still have, of course,
وأصبح لدينا عالم متصل. ولكن ما يزال هناك, بالطبع
Congo, up there. We still have as poor countries
الكونغو, في الأعلى هناك. ما زال هناك بلدان فقيرة
as we have had, always, in history.
كما كان الحال دائما في التاريخ.
And that's the bottom billion, where we've heard today
أما عن المليار شخص الأكثر فقرا, فقد رأينا اليوم
about a completely new approach to do it.
طريقة جديدة للنظر اليه
And how fast has this happened?
وبأي سرعة يحدث كل هذا؟
Well, MDG 4.
بالنسبة لل MDG 4 (أهداف التنمية للألفية): الحد من وفيات الأطفال
The United States has not been so eager
فأن الولايات المتحدة لم تبد الكثير من الحماس
to use MDG 4.
لتطبيقه
But you have been the main sponsor that has enabled us to measure it,
ولكن كنتم الممول الرئيسي الذي أتاح لنا قياس التقدم الحاصل في تطبيقه
because it's the only child mortality that we can measure.
لأن معدل وفيات الأطفال هو المعيار الوحيد الذي نستطيع قياسه.
And we used to say that it should fall four percent per year.
وقد اعتدنا ان نقول أنه يجب أن يتناقص بمعدل 4% بالسنة
Let's see what Sweden has done.
فلننظر ماذا فعلت السويد
We used to boast about fast social progress.
فقد اعتدنا التباهي بتطورنا الأجتماعي السريع
That's where we were, 1900.
هنا حيث كنا في سنة 1900
1900, Sweden was there.
سنة 1900, السويد كانت هنا
Same child mortality as Bangladesh had, 1990,
نفس معدل وفيات الأطفال في بنغلادش سنة 1990
though they had lower income.
مع أن دخلهم أدنى.
They started very well. They used the aid well.
فقد انطلقوا انطلاقة قوية. لقد احسنوا استعمال المساعدات
They vaccinated the kids. They get better water.
ولقحوا الأطفال. وحسنوا نوعية المياه
And they reduced child mortality,
وخفضوا وفيات الأطفال
with an amazing 4.7 percent per year. They beat Sweden.
مع نسبة مذهلة, 4.7% بالسنة. لقد هزموا السويد
I run Sweden the same 16 year period.
فقد درست السويد على نفس فترة 16 عاما
Second round, it's Sweden, 1916,
الجولة الثانية: السويد سنة 1916
against Egypt, 1990.
في مقابل مصر عام 1990
Here we go. Once again the USA is part of the reason here.
ها نحن ننطلق. مرة أخرى الولايات المتحدة ساهمت في هذه النتيجة
They get safe water, they get food for the poor,
فمصر أمنت المياه النظيفة, والطعام للفقراء.
and they get malaria eradicated.
وتخلصوا من الملاريا.
5.5 percent. They are faster than the millennium development goal.
5.5%. لقد حققوا نتيجة أفضل من هدف التنمية للألفية(MDG 4)
And third chance for Sweden, against Brazil here.
والفرصة الثالثة للسويد, في مواجهة البرازيل هذه المرة
Brazil here has amazing social improvement
والبرازيل هنا لديها تنمية اجتماعية مذهلة
over the last 16 years,
خلال الستة عشر عاما الأخيرة
and they go faster than Sweden.
وقد كانوا أسرع من السويد.
This means that the world is converging.
مما يعني أن العالم يصبح أكثر تقاربا
The middle income countries,
البلدان ذات الدخل المتوسط,
the emerging economy, they are catching up.
البلدان الناشئة, انهم يقتربون من الدول المتطورة
They are moving to cities,
انهم يستقرون في المدن
where they also get better assistance for that.
حيث يستطيعون الحصول على خدمات أفضل.
Well the Swedish students protest at this point.
السويديون قد يعترضون على هذه المقارنة
They say, "This is not fair,
فقد يقولون:"هذه المقارنة ليست عادلة,
because these countries had vaccines and antibiotics
لأن هذه البلدان حصلت على اللقاحات والمضادات الحيوية
that were not available for Sweden.
التي لم تكن تتوفر في السويد في ذلك الزمان.
We have to do real-time competition."
يجب أن نقارن بينهم على نفس الفترة."
Okay. I give you Singapore, the year I was born.
حسنا. فلنأخذ سنغافورة, في السنة التي ولدت فيها
Singapore had twice the child mortality of Sweden.
معدل وفيات الأطفال في سنغافورة كان ضعف معدل السويد
It's the most tropical country in the world,
انه البلد الأكثر استوائية في العالم.
a marshland on the equator.
مستنقع على خط الاستواء
And here we go. It took a little time for them to get independent.
فلنبدأ. لقد استغرقوا بعض الوقت حتى نالوا استقلالهم
But then they started to grow their economy.
ثم بدأوا بتنمية اقتصادهم
And they made the social investment. They got away malaria.
واستثمروا في التنمية الاجتماعية. وتخلصوا من الملاريا
They got a magnificent health system
فحصلوا على نظام صحي مدهش
that beat both the U.S. and Sweden.
تقدموا حتى على الولايات المتحدة والسويد
We never thought it would happen that they would win over Sweden!
لم نكن نتخيل انهم سيتفوقون على السويد
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
All these green countries are achieving millennium development goals.
كل هذه البلدان, باللون الأخضر, تحقق أهداف التنمية للألفية
These yellow are just about to be doing this.
أما البلدان باللون الأصفر فأنهم على وشك تحقيق هذه الأهداف
These red are the countries that doesn't do it, and the policy has to be improved.
بينما البلدان بالأحمر فلم ينجحوا, ويجب أن يحسنوا سياساتهم
Not simplistic extrapolation.
لا يوجد استقراء بسيط
We have to really find a way
علينا ان نجد وسيلة
of supporting those countries in a better way.
لندعم هذه الدول بطريقة أفضل
We have to respect the middle income countries
علينا أن نحترم الدول ذات الدخل المتوسط
on what they are doing.
لما يحققونه
And we have to fact-base the whole way we look at the world.
وعلينا أن نبني نظرتنا للعالم على أساس الحقائق
This is dollar per person. This is HIV in the countries.
هذا الدخل الفردي(بالدولار). وهذا معدل الأيدز في الدول
The blue is Africa.
الأزرق يمثل أفريقيا
The size of the bubbles is how many are HIV affected.
حجم الفقاعات يمثل عدد المصابين بالأيدز
You see the tragedy in South Africa there.
هل ترون المأساة في جنوب أفريقيا هناك
About 20 percent of the adult population are infected.
حوالي 20% من الراشدين مصابين بهذا المرض
And in spite of them having quite a high income,
وعلى الرغم من أنهم يتمتعون بدخل مرتفع
they have a huge number of HIV infected.
فان لديهم عددا كبيرا من المصابين بالأيدز.
But you also see that there are African countries down here.
وتستطيعون أيضا رؤية الدول الأفريقية في الأسفل هنا
There is no such thing as an HIV epidemic in Africa.
ليس هناك وباء أيدز في أفريقيا
There's a number, five to 10 countries in Africa
ولكن هناك عدد, 5 الى 10 دول في أفريقيا
that has the same level as Sweden and United States.
لديها نفس مستوى السويد والولايات المتحدة
And there are others who are extremely high.
بينما هناك دول أخرى مع معدلات مرتفعة جدا
And I will show you that what has happened
وسأشرح لكم ما حدث
in one of the best countries, with the most vibrant economy
في بلد من أفضل بلدان أفريقيا, ويتمتع بأفضل حيوية اقتصادية
in Africa and a good governance, Botswana.
في أفريقيا, وقيادة جيدة, وهو بوتسوانا
They have a very high level. It's coming down.
لديهم معدل مرتفع جدا. وقد بدأ بالأنخفاض
But now it's not falling,
ولكن الأن لم يعد يتراجع
because there, with help from PEPFAR,
لأنه, وبمساعدة PEPFAR
it's working with treatment. And people are not dying.
فانهم يحصلون على علاج. والمصابين لايموتون بسرعة
And you can see it's not that easy,
وكما تتوقعون فان الأمر ليس سهلا
that it is war which caused this.
فالحرب لم تكن وراء هذا
Because here, in Congo, there is war.
لأنه في الكونغو, هناك حرب
And here, in Zambia, there is peace.
وفي زامبيا هناك سلام
And it's not the economy. Richer country has a little higher.
وليس الاقتصاد. فالدول الأغنى لديها معدل أعلى بقليل
If I split Tanzania in its income,
واذا قسمت تنزانيا حسب المدخول
the richer 20 percent in Tanzania
فان ال20% الأغنى في تنزانيا
has more HIV than the poorest one.
عندهم معدل اصابة بالأيدز أعلى من الأفقر
And it's really different within each country.
والمعدل فعلا مختلف داخل كل بلد
Look at the provinces of Kenya. They are very different.
انظروا الى المحافظات في كينيا. انهم مختلفون كليا
And this is the situation you see.
وهذه الوضعية, هل ترون
It's not deep poverty. It's the special situation,
انها ليست بسبب الفقر المدقع. انها حالة خاصة
probably of concurrent sexual partnership
على الأرجح تتعلق بعدد الشركاء الجنسيين
among part of the heterosexual population
في قسم من السكان
in some countries, or some parts of countries,
في بعض الدول, أو في بعض المناطق في الدول
in south and eastern Africa.
في جنوب وشرق أفريقيا.
Don't make it Africa. Don't make it a race issue.
لا تعبروا هذه المشكلة مشكلة افريقيا او مسألة عرقية
Make it a local issue. And do prevention at each place,
اعتبروها مشكلة محلية. وحاولوا تطبيق الوقاية في كل مكان
in the way it can be done there.
بطريقة تتلاءم مع المكان
So to just end up,
حتى أختم:
there are things of suffering
هناك أشياء في معاناة
in the one billion poorest, which we don't know.
الأفقر مليار انسان, لا نعلمها
Those who live beyond the cellphone,
هؤلاء الذين يعيشون بعيدا عن الهواتف النقالة,
those who have yet to see a computer,
هؤلاء الذين لم يروا بعد حاسوبا,
those who have no electricity at home.
وليس لديهم كهرباء في منازلهم.
This is the disease, Konzo, I spent 20 years
هذا داء كونزو, الذي أمضيت 20 عاما
elucidating in Africa.
في دراسته في أفريقيا
It's caused by fast processing of toxic cassava root in famine situation.
ينتج عن التجهيز السريع لجذور الكسافا السامة, في حالات المجاعة.
It's similar to the pellagra epidemic in Mississippi in the '30s.
انه مشابه للحصاف في المسيسبي في الثلاثينات
It's similar to other nutritional diseases.
انه مشابه لبقية الامراض الناتجة عن سوء التغذية
It will never affect a rich person.
ولن يصيب ابد شخصا غنيا
We have seen it here in Mozambique.
وقد لاحظنا وجوده هنا في موزمبيق
This is the epidemic in Mozambique. This is an epidemic in northern Tanzania.
هذه صور الوباء في موزمبيق. وهنا في شمال تنزانيا
You never heard about the disease.
لم تسمعوا ابدا عن هذا الوباء
But it's much more than Ebola
ولكن هناك عدد أكبر من المصابين بهذا المرض
that has been affected by this disease.
من المصابين بالأيبولا
Cause crippling throughout the world.
هذا المرض يتسبب باعاقات في كل العالم
And over the last two years,
وخلال العامين الأخيرين
2,000 people has been crippled
تسبب باعاقة 2000 شخص
in the southern tip of Bandundu region.
في الطرف الجنوبي من منطقة بندوندا
That used to be the illegal diamond trade,
هذه المنطقة كانت مركزا للتجارة غير المشروعة بالماس
from the UNITA-dominated area in Angola.
من المنطقة التي يسيطر عليها UNITA في أنغولا
That has now disappeared,
كل هذا اختفى الان
and they are now in great economic problem.
ولديهم الان مشكل اقتصادي كبير
And one week ago, for the first time,
الأسبوع الماضي, وللمرة الأولى,
there were four lines on the Internet.
حصلوا على 4 خطوط انترنت
Don't get confused of the progress of the emerging economies
لا تقللوا من أهمية الدول الناشئة
and the great capacity
والقدرة العظيمة
of people in the middle income countries
للشعوب في الدول ذات الدخل المتوسط
and in peaceful low income countries.
والدول ذات الدخل المنخفض, ولكن تتمتع بالسلام
There is still mystery in one billion.
لا يزال هناك الكثير مما يجب فعله مع المليار
And we have to have more concepts
وعلينا أن نكون وجهة نظر أعمق من
than just developing countries and developing world.
"العالم النامي" و"الدول النامية"
We need a new mindset. The world is converging,
نحتاج الى طريقة تفكير جديدة. العالم يصبح أكثر تجانسا
but -- but -- but not the bottom billion.
ولكن, لكن, ...لكن ليس المليار الأكثر فقرا
They are still as poor as they've ever been.
ما يزالون فقراء كما كانوا دائما
It's not sustainable, and it will not happen around one superpower.
وهذا يجب أن يتغير. ولا يتعلق الأمر بقوة عظمى وحيدة
But you will remain
ولكن ستبقون
one of the most important superpowers,
واحدة من أهم القوى العظمى
and the most hopeful superpower, for the time to be.
وأكثر قوة عظمى واعدة, في الوقت الحاضر
And this institution
وهذه المؤسسة
will have a very crucial role,
ستلعب دورا محوريا
not for United States, but for the world.
ليس فقط في الولايات المتحدة ولكن في العالم كله
So you have a very bad name,
لذلك اسم قسمكم ليس مناسبا,
State Department. This is not the State Department.
وزارة الخارجية الأمريكية, هذه ليست وزارة الخارجية,
It's the World Department.
هذه وزارة خارجية العالم
And we have a high hope in you. Thank you very much.
ولدينا أمل كبير فيكم. شكرا جزيلا
(Applause)
(تصفيق)